You can't protect them entirely from risky
behaviors and nor should you, in some
ways, because it's part of growing up.
It's part of how they learn and
it's part of how they develop.
And I think again, I keep going back
to my previous experience, but I think
what happens with young people who are
in foster care or young people that are
in residential homes, is that there's
more of a microscope on them because
it's kind of, even if the foster carer
or the people in the home are great
and love the kid and really want to be
there for them, they are still being
employed and they are being watched.
So I think there can be a tendency to stop
any risky behavior and just cut it off.
And I think that that can be really
damaging in some ways 'cause I
think that maybe kids don't get to
experiment, they don't get to grow.
And also in some other ways they
might just go and do more risky
stuff behind their parents' back.
The best way to sort of support and
manage those risky behaviors is again,
it's just some openness and some honesty
it's like, you know, to talk to your
kid about these things and not sort
of shy away from them without judgment
and without telling them off for them.
That's the thing that really
surprises some young people when
they come to sessions with us is
this thing of they might tell you
they've done something and you might
tell them, "oh God, that doesn't,
you know, that sounds a bit risky".
But you're not judging them and
you're not telling them off and
I think they expect that because
that's kind of what they've learned.
So I think it's just openness.
It's honesty.
It's sort of, talking to them about
the risks, but also showing some
understanding and not just punishing them.
I think punishing people is the
worst thing you can do in some
respects, obviously there's levels
where you have to, but I think to
just sort of automatically punish
risky behavior when it's just part
of teenage life isn't really helpful.